最专业冰火字幕
诚意奉献
专注GOT剧集
翻译 兮迩CeCe
翻译 Noxumos
翻译 Joker
君临 King's Landing
红堡
Red Keep
翻译 FreezeBlade
校对 屈畅   赵琳
派
Pyke
克
城
校对 拉拉兄控凯冯  北落师门
后期 SerGawen@huiji.wiki
临冬城
Winterfell
监制 北落师门
监制 临冬城的狮子
最专业的华语冰火资料站：        冰与火之歌中文维基
http://asoiaf.huiji.wiki
技术支持 灰机T.R.A.N.S.
绝境长城 the Wall
策划 衣柜军团
联合出品
史诗图书 | 冰火中文维基 | 黑城堡奇幻微刊
Epic Books         ASOIAF.huiji.wiki          Heichengbao
史诗图书  正统奇幻的圣殿
特别顾问 屈畅(ccxx)@史诗图书
维斯·多斯拉克
Vaes Dothrak
弥林
Meereen
根据长篇小说
《冰与火之歌》 改编
原著  乔治·R·R·马丁
权力的游戏
衣柜字幕组
协力制作
史诗图书
Epic Books
冰火中文维基
ASOIAF.HuiJi.WiKi
黑城堡
EPICASTLE
第四集
陌客之书
Book of the Stranger
长爪
瓦雷利亚钢剑
忧郁的艾迪
守夜人
你要去哪？
Where you gonna go?
南方
South.
去干什么？
What are you gonna do?
琼恩·雪诺
取暖
Get warm.
我和你在艰难屯的时候
I was with you at Hardhome.
我们看到了外面有什么
We saw what's out there.
我们都知道他们往这来了
We know it's coming here.
你怎能在这时抛下我们？
How can you leave us now?
我能做的我都做了 你知道的
I did everything I could. You know that.
- 你发过誓 - 是的 我把我的生命献给了守夜人
- You swore a vow. - Aye, I pledged my life to the Night's Watch.
- 我付出了我的生命 - “夜夜皆然”
- I gave my life. - For all nights to come.
他们杀了我 艾迪！我的兄弟们
They killed me, Edd! My own brothers.
你还想让我留在这里？
You want me to stay here after that?
有人来了！
Riders approaching!
打开大门！
Open the gate!
珊莎·史塔克
塔斯的布蕾妮
“美人”
波德瑞克·派恩
侍从
托蒙德
野人头领
汤很好喝
This is good soup.
你还记得老奶妈以前常做的腰花馅饼吗？
Do you remember those kidney pies Old Nan used to make?
加了豌豆和洋葱的？
With the peas and onions?
我们一开始就不该离开临冬城
We never should have left Winterfell.
你不希望回到我们离开的那天吗？
Don't you wish we could go back to the day we left?
我真想对着我自己大喊“别去啊 白痴”
I want to scream at myself, "Don't go, you idiot."
我们怎么会知道？
How could we know?
我花了很多时间回想当初我对你有多么混蛋
I spent a lot of time thinking about what an ass I was to you.
我真希望我能改变一切
I wish I could change everything.
我们那时只是孩子
We were children.
就承认吧 我很讨人厌
I was awful, just admit it.
你偶尔有些讨厌
You were occasionally awful.
但我肯定我是很无趣的
I'm sure I can't have been great fun.
总是在你们一起玩的时候缩在墙角闷闷不乐
Always sulking in the corner while the rest of you played.
- 你能原谅我吗？ - 没什么好原谅的
- Can you forgive me? - There's nothing to forgive.
- 原谅我 -好吧
- Forgive me. - All right.
好吧 我原谅你
All right, I forgive you.
你觉得都几千年了
You'd think after thousands of years,
守夜人总该学会怎么酿出好酒吧
the Night's Watch would have learned how to make a good ale.
你要去哪儿？
Where will you go?
我们要去哪儿？
Where will we go?
要是我不照看着你 父亲的在天之灵不会放过我的
If I don't watch over you, Father's ghost will come back and murder me.
我们要去哪儿？
Where will we go?
我不能待在这了 在发生了这些事以后
I can't stay here, not after what happened.
我们只有一个地方可以去
There's only one place we can go.
家
Home.
我们是该叫波顿打铺盖卷走人吗？
Should we tell the Boltons to pack up and leave?
我们会从他们手里夺回来的
We'll take it back from them.
我没有军队
I don't have an army.
你救了多少野人？
How many wildlings did you save?
他们不是来这为我效命的
They didn't come here to serve me.
他们的命是你给的
They owe you their lives.
你觉得有卢斯·波顿继续做北境守护他们会安全吗？
You think they'll be safe here if Roose Bolton remains Warden of the North?
- 珊莎 -临冬城是我们的家
- Sansa. - Winterfell is our home.
是我们的 也是艾莉亚 布兰和瑞肯的
It's ours and Arya's and Bran's and Rickon's.
不管他们在哪 它都属于我们家族
Wherever they are, it belongs to our family.
我们必须为它而战
We have to fight for it.
我已经厌倦战斗了
I'm tired of fighting.
自从离家我就一直在战斗
It's all I've done since I left home.
我杀过守夜人的兄弟
I've killed brothers of the Night's Watch.
我杀过野人 我杀过我敬仰的人
I've killed wildlings. I've killed men that I admire.
我绞死了一个比布兰还小的男孩
I hanged a boy younger than Bran.
我战斗过 却失败了
I fought and I lost.
如果我们不夺回北境 我们永远不会安全
If we don't take back the North, we'll never be safe.
我需要你帮助我
I want you to help me.
但如果有必要 我会亲自动手
But I'll do it myself if I have to.
女士
My lady.
戴佛斯爵士
Ser Davos.
梅丽珊卓
红衣祭司
戴佛斯·席渥斯
洋葱骑士
你会留在黑城堡吗？
Will you stay here at Castle Black?
我会谨遵琼恩·雪诺的命令
I will do as Jon Snow commands.
你现在效命琼恩·雪诺了？
You serve Jon Snow now?
他是预言中的王子
He's the prince that was promised.
原谅我 女士 我还以为那是史坦尼斯
Forgive me, my lady, I thought that was Stannis.
你们那边发生了什么？
What happened down there?
打了场仗 史坦尼斯被打败了
There was a battle. Stannis was defeated.
那席琳呢？
And Shireen?
公主怎么样了？
What happened to the princess?
我看到了发生的事
I saw what happened.
我看到史坦尼斯的大军被击溃
I saw Stannis' forces defeated in the field.
女士 我是戴佛斯·席渥斯爵士
My lady, I'm Ser Davos Seaworth.
我们见过
We've met before.
我那时是蓝礼·拜拉席恩的御林铁卫
I was Kingsguard to Renly Baratheon.
直到蓝礼被血魔法暗杀而死
Before Renly was assassinated with bloodmagic.
那已经过去了
That's in the past now.
是的 是过去了
Yes, it's in the past.
并不意味着我忘掉了
It doesn't mean I forget.
或原谅了
Or forgive.
他承认了 你知道的
He admitted it, you know.
谁？
Who did?
史坦尼斯
Stannis.
就在我处决他之前
Just before I executed him.
罗宾·艾林
鹰巢城公爵 谷地守护
约恩·罗伊斯
“青铜”
培提尔·贝里席
“小指头”
谷地守护者！
The Defender of the Vale!
培提尔叔叔！
Uncle Petyr!
大人
My lord.
过来瞧
Come and see.
我错过了你的命名日 来吧
I missed your name day. Go on.
猎鹰！
A falcon!
是矛隼
A gyrfalcon.
最名贵最稀有的鸟
The greatest and rarest of birds.
贝里席 上次我见到你的时候
Last time I saw you, Baelish,
你告诉我你要带着珊莎·史塔克回到五指半岛
you told me you were taking Sansa Stark home with you to the Fingers.
我是这样做了
Indeed I was.
但是不久前我们收到报告
And yet not long ago, we received reports
说她嫁给了临冬城的拉姆斯·波顿
that she has been married to Ramsay Bolton in Winterfell.
去五指半岛的路上 我们遭到了一大批波顿军队的袭击
On our way to the Fingers, we were set upon by a large force of Bolton men.
他们似乎明确地知道我们何时出行
Seemed to know exactly when we were traveling
也明确地知道我们护送的是谁
and exactly whom we were transporting.
你把我当白痴吗？
Do you take me for a fool?
告诉我 罗伊斯大人
Tell me, Lord Royce,
有多少人知道我与珊莎·史塔克的出行计划？
how many people knew of my travel plans with Sansa Stark?
我只把我的打算告诉过你
I shared my intentions with you
别无二人
and no one else.
在别人家里诽谤别人
Slander a man in his own home,
接下来便是兵戎相见
you might find yourself crossing swords with him.
你的家属于谷地 而谷地主人就站在我们面前
Your home is the Vale. The Lord of the Vale stands before us.
主人说了算
And only his judgment concerns me.
我们应该把他扔下月门吗？
Shall we throw him through the Moon Door?
大人
My lord.
大人 我一直对艾林家族尽诚竭节
My lord, I have always been faithful to House Arryn.
无论是对令尊 令堂 还是现在的您
To your father, to your mother, and now to you.
你相信他吗 培提尔叔叔？
Do you believe him, Uncle Petyr?
罗伊斯大人竭力效忠谷地
Lord Royce has served the Vale well.
戎马多年 战绩彪炳
He's enjoyed a distinguished military career.
如果他的忠诚值得信任
If we could trust his absolute loyalty,
那么在即将到来的征战中他仍是总司令的绝佳人选
he would make a capable commander in the wars to come.
您大可相信我的绝对忠诚 大人
You can trust my absolute loyalty, my lord.
我认为他值得一次机会 您觉得呢？
I think he deserves one more chance. What do you say?
好吧
Fine.
我带来了好消息
I bring good news.
我在北境的朋友告诉我珊莎·史塔克逃出了临冬城
My friends in the North tell me Sansa has escaped Winterfell.
我估计她已经去往黑城堡了
I expect she's headed to Castle Black
她的哥哥在那里做总司令
where her brother serves as Lord Commander.
但她在那不安全 波顿正在追捕她
But she won't be safe there, not with the Boltons after her.
她是我表姐
She's my cousin.
我们应该帮助她
We should help her.
我的第一反应也是这个
That was my instinct as well.
公爵已经发话了
Our lord has spoken.
集合谷地的骑士
Gather the Knights of the Vale.
加入战争的时候到了
The time has come to join the fray.
你把敌人请进了我们的城市？
You invite the enemy into our city?
是的
I did.
一位智者曾经告诉我
As a clever man once told me,
提利昂·兰尼斯特
“小恶魔”
瓦里斯
“八爪蜘蛛”
灰虫子
弥桑黛
“需要握手言和的是敌人 而不是朋友”
"We make peace with our enemies, not our friends."
我不跟女王的敌人握手言和
I don't make peace with the queen's enemies.
我会杀死他们
I kill the queen's enemies.
对 那是军事手段
Yes, that's the military approach.
在弥林发挥了什么作用？
And how has that worked here in Meereen?
我表达的是外交手段
I represent the diplomatic approach.
女王试过与伟主们言和
Our queen tried to make peace with the Masters
他们却想要杀她
and they tried to murder her.
我们谈判时留点神
We enter these negotiations with open eyes.
相信我 我近期的奴隶经历
Trust me. My own recent experience with slavery
已经告诉我这项制度有多可怕了
has taught me the horrors of that institution.
您做了几天的奴隶呢？
How many days were you a slave?
长到够我知道了
Long enough to know.
没有长到够你了解
Not long enough to understand.
我用一个辉币买了这个侏儒
I bought this dwarf for a single gold honor.
不知何故你竟飞黄腾达
And somehow you've risen
都住到弥林的大金字塔顶来了
to the top of the Great Pyramid of Meereen.
真让人称奇不已
It's most impressive.
现在你还代替阿斯塔波的善主发言呢
And now you speak for the Good Masters of Astapor.
敬时来运转
Here's to reversals of fortune.
我们是来这觐见女王的
We came here to meet the queen
结果 迎接我们的是侏儒和太监
and instead we're greeted by a dwarf and a eunuch.
让我们摊开了说吧 好吗？说说你们想要什么
Let's make this simple, shall we? Tell me what you want.
我们想要你们离开奴隶湾
We want you to leave Slaver's Bay.
带上你们的龙和雇佣兵 走人
Take your dragons and your mercenaries and go.
丹妮莉丝女王不会永远待在弥林的
Queen Daenerys won't stay in Meereen forever.
她的目标在西方
Her path takes her westward.
我们上次见面的时候 我提出给她船只
When we last met, I offered her ships
这样她就可以回到属于她的维斯特洛 但她拒绝了
so she could return to Westeros where she belongs. She refused them.
她拒绝了 是因为成千上万的
She refused them because hundreds of thousands
男人女人和孩子还活在链铐之下
of men, women, and children still lived in chains.
他们自古以来就是如此
As they have since the dawn of time.
- 不再是了 - 你觉得你现在就是自由人了吗？
- Not anymore. - You think you're a free man now?
你还是在遵令行事
You still follow orders.
你的主人有银发和奶子
Just because your master has silver hair and tits
并不意味着她就不是奴隶主
doesn't mean she's not a master.
朋友 朋友 朋友 拜托
Friends, friends, friends, please.
世上总是有有钱有势的人和一无所有的人
There have always been those with wealth and power and those with nothing.
世界的规则就是这样 我不是来改变世界规则的
That is the way of the world. I'm not here to change the way of the world.
奴隶制就是我们世界的规则
Slavery is the way of our world.
你们不是非得用奴隶来赚钱
You don't need slaves to make money.
维斯特洛几百年来都没有奴隶
There haven't been slaves in Westeros for hundreds of years
我却比你们中任何一个都富有
and I grew up richer than any of you.
不过 我们的女王却发现她错在
But our queen recognizes that she erred
只是废除奴隶制
by abolishing slavery
却没有提供一个新的体系来取代它
without providing a new system to replace it.
所以这里是女王的提议
So here is the queen's proposal.
奴隶制永不回到弥林
Slavery will never return to Meereen,
但她会给奴隶湾的其他城市
but she will give the other cities of Slaver's Bay
一些时间来调整到新的秩序
time to adjust to the new order.
什么意思？
What does that mean?
废除奴隶制不必一夜完成
Instead of abolishing slavery overnight,
可以宽限到七年
we will give you seven years to end the practice.
奴隶主将获得补偿
Slaveholders will be compensated
价格公道
for their losses, of course, at fair prices.
作为交换 你们要停止
In exchange, you will cut off
对鹰身女妖之子的支持
your support for the Sons of the Harpy.
鹰身女妖之子和我们无关
We do not support the Sons of the Harpy.
好吧 随意了 总之你们会停止支持
Fine, fine, but you will cut it off all the same.
我希望你们接受 朋友们
I do hope you accept, my friends.
你们不会得到更好的条件了
You will not receive a better offer.
让我们扬帆于自由之潮
Let us sail on the tide of freedom
而不是被它吞没
instead of being drowned by it.
我还给尊贵的客人们准备了点离别的礼物……
And as a parting gift to our honored guests...
给自由一个机会吧
Give freedom a chance.
它仍与从前一样甜美
See if it doesn't taste every bit as good as what came before.
我的朋友们！
My friends!
大大的抱歉
Large sorry...
让你们等了‘肥肠’久的时间
...you wait so fat time.
要不我来替你作翻译吧
Perhaps I should translate for you.
我们会说通用语
We speak the Common Tongue.
- 真棒 - 今天你和奴隶贩子们见了面
- Excellent. - You met with the slavers today.
没错
I did.
我们的兄弟姐妹们在和这些渣滓抗争的路上前仆后继
Our brothers and sisters died fighting this scum.
而你现在却邀请他们登堂入室 共饮美酒
Now you invite them to our city and drink wine with them.
我想建筑这个大厅的目的
I imagine this room was built
是让统治者威慑被统治者
so the rulers could intimidate the ruled.
但我不是你们的统治者
But I am not your ruler.
不是解放者
I'm not the Breaker of Chains.
不是不焚者
I'm not the Unburnt.
更不是龙之母
And I am certainly not the Mother of Dragons.
你在这里只是一个陌生人
You are a stranger here.
凭什么代表弥林和我们的敌人进行谈判？
So why do you represent Meereen in these talks with our enemies?
因为我们的女王选择我作为她的顾问
Because our queen chose me as her advisor.
直到陛下旅途归来
Until she returns from her travels...
她什么时候才能回来？
When does she return?
很快 我向你们保证
Soon. You have my word.
我们不认识你 更不信任你 我们熟知的是灰虫子
We don't know you. We don't trust you. We know Torgo Nudho.
我们随他抗击伟主 我们信任他
We fight with him against the Masters. We trust him.
这正是灰虫子参与谈判的原因
And that is exactly why Grey Worm took part in these negotiations.
作为无垢者军团的指挥官 他知道如何打败奴隶贩子
As commander of the Unsullied, he knows how to defeat the slavers
但他同样知道什么时候应该缔造和平
and he knows when it is time to make peace.
你和那群奴隶贩子握手言和？
You have made peace with the slavers?
我们提出了条件
We offered terms.
你呢？灰虫子
And you, Grey Worm?
你想和那群将我们从母亲的臂弯中夺走
You want to drink wine with these men?
像牲畜般竞标拍卖的人一起把酒言欢吗？
The men who tore us from our mothers' arms and and sold us at auction like cattle?
我是士兵 不是政客
I am a soldier, not a politician.
但如果有机会缔结和平
But if there is a chance for peace --
公正的和平
a <i>just</i> peace --
我们应该把握住
we should take it.
弥桑黛
Missandei,
你知道那些人的真面目 你怎能信任他们？
you know what these men are. How can you trust them?
我不信任他们 从未有过
I do not trust them. I will never trust them.
但有位智者曾经说过
But as a wise man once said,
需要握手言和的是敌人 而不是朋友
"We make peace with our enemies, not our friends. "
- 不要搬我出来圆你的谎话 - 那些人尊重你
- Do not use me for your lies. - Those men respect you.
他们尊重我是因为他们对我知根知底
They respect me because they know who I am.
- 他们深知我的忠诚 - 我也一样
- They know I am loyal. - As do I.
我对女王陛下忠诚 而不是对你
I am loyal to my queen, not you.
如果你胆敢背叛她的事业 你就将是我之敌
If you betray her work, you are my enemy.
我没有背叛她的事业 我正试图挽救她的城市
I am not betraying her work. I am trying to save her city.
你向奴隶主承诺他们可以保留奴隶制
You promised the slavers they could keep slavery.
短期之内
For a short time.
七年对奴隶来说可不是什么短期
Seven years is not a short time for a slave.
你说得对
You're right.
奴隶制可怖 应当即刻根除
Slavery is a horror that should be ended at once.
战争可怖 应当马上停止
War is a horror that should be ended at once.
但我没法两头兼顾
I can't do both today.
你不该信任那些人
You are wrong to trust these men.
我信任的不是奴隶主 而是他们为自己打算的心思
I don't trust the Masters. I trust their self-interest.
如果他们确信与我合作对他们自己有利
They're trustworthy if they're convinced
那他们就可以被相信
that working with me is in their self-interest.
你不知道他们 你不了解他们
You don't know them. You don't understand them.
我们在他们眼里根本不是人
We are not human in their eyes.
当他们看向我 看到的是一把武器
They look at me and see a weapon.
当他们看向她 看到的是一个娼妓
They look at her and see a whore.
当他们看向我 看到的是一个畸形的小怪兽
They look at me and they see a misshapen little beast.
他们的蔑视造就他们的弱点
Their contempt is their weakness.
他们会低估我们 而我们会利用这一点
They'll underestimate us every time and we will use that to our advantage.
他们不可能为你所用
You will not use them.
他们会利用你 这是他们的天性
They will use you. That is what they do.
达里奥·纳哈里斯
雇佣兵
你还好吗？
You all right?
何不坐下来喘口气呢？
Why don't you sit and catch your breath?
我很好
I'm fine.
我觉得你骑不了龙
I don't think you could ride the dragon.
换做二十年前 也许可以
20 years ago, maybe.
- 什么？ - 我们的女王
- What? - Our queen.
别看她很娇小 你懂的 其实她很狂野
She's wild, you know. Don't let her size fool you.
我这么年轻都难以招架
It's hard enough for me and I'm a young man.
你呢 我担心你的心脏受不了
You, I don't think your heart could take it.
女王陛下选择了我一定让你非常不爽
Must make you angry that our queen chose me.
我很难过 过不了太久你就会辜负她
Makes me sad. You'll disappoint her before long.
- 她会忘了你 - 我们都好景不长
- She'll move on. - We'll all disappoint her before long.
现在我们需要彼此 当我们不再需要彼此的时候……
We need each other right now. After we're done needing each other...
乔拉·莫尔蒙
“大熊”
喔 我可不想和你打 安达尔人乔拉
Oh, I don't want to fight you, Jorah the Andal.
我能有什么好处？
What do I have to gain?
如果我赢了 我就成了干翻一个老家伙的草包
If I win, I'm the shit who killed an old man.
万一我输了 我就成了被一个老家伙干翻的草包
If I lose, I'm the shit who was killed by an old man.
你小时候没受过多少管束 是吧？
You didn't get much discipline as a child, did you?
一点没有
None.
这条路直穿马门
The road running through the Horse Gate,
他们叫它众神大道
they call that the godsway.
东市 西市
Eastern Market, Western Market.
卓戈卡奥死后 她本该来到这里 加入那些遗孀
When Khal Drogo died, she was supposed to come here and join the Dosh Khaleen
成为多希卡林的一员
the widows of the dead khals.
那就是他们要带她去的地方
That's where they would have taken her
多希卡林神庙
the Temple of the Dosh Khaleen.
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
这座马族圣城禁止携带武器出入
It's forbidden to carry weapons in the sacred city.
难道潜入城中偷走他们的卡丽熙就不禁止吗？
Isn't it forbidden to sneak into their city and steal their khaleesi?
如果他们发现了我们 而我们手无寸铁
If they spot us and we're unarmed,
我们就说我们是要去西市的商人
we'll say we're traders heading for the Western Market.
但如果他们看到武器……
But if they see weapons...
你这是在要求一条狗交出它的牙
You're asking a dog to hand over his teeth.
下面有十万人
There's 100,000 of them down there.
我们不能硬闯
We can't fight our way out.
我们等到天黑 然后找到她
We wait till dark, and then we'll find her.
这把刀和我有很深的羁绊
I'm very attached to this knife.
别担心 不会碰到你
Don't worry. It didn't touch you.
你知道这意味着什么？
You know what happens?
我知道这意味着什么
I know what happens.
我自己来吧
I'll do it myself.
我应该投胎成一个多斯拉克人的
I should have been born a Dothraki.
走吧
Come on.
朋友们
My friends...
我们从西市来 在城里迷路了
We wandered off from the Western Market and got lost.
您二位能告诉我们怎么回去吗？
Could you show us the way back?
你们卖的是什么？
What do you sell?
酒
Wine.
明天来我的货摊
Come down to my stall tomorrow,
我一定奉上一桶青亭岛的佳酿
I'll give you a cask of the Arbor's finest.
你们不是商人
You're not merchants.
去叫人来
Get the others.
告诉过你这把刀和我的羁绊很深的
Told you, I'm very attached to this knife.
你还好吧？
You all right?
如果他们发现一具被捅死的尸体
If they find a body with a stab wound,
全城的人都会出动搜查我们
the whole city will be looking for us.
她们有些人认为多斯拉克人不该与外族通婚
Some of them don't think Dothraki should breed with foreigners.
丹妮莉丝·坦格利安
弥林的女王
那群老蠢妇 她们从未察觉我们一直在稀释原始的血脉
They are stupid old women. They don't realize that we have always diluted our blood.
这一个 是拉札人
This one is Lhazareen.
她的卡奥放火烧掉她的村子后发现了躲在井底的她
Her Khal found her hiding in a well after he burned her village.
你那时多大？
How old were you?
十二岁
Twelve.
一年之后 她给她的卡奥诞下了一个女儿 当时他是怎样的欣喜若狂？
A year later, she bore her Khal a daughter. How did he show his happiness?
他打断了我的肋骨
He broke my ribs.
我们不是这里的女王 但卡奥们倚仗我们的智慧
We are not queens here, but the khals depend on us for our wisdom.
我们的生活充满意义
Our lives have meaning.
比起多数人而言
That is more than most have.
卡奥们明晚在卡拉萨大会聚首时 我希望他们能让你与我们一起度过余生
When the khals meet for the Khalar Vezhven tomorrow night, I hope they let you live out your days with us.
其他的结果可就没那么舒服了
The other possibilities are not so pleasant.
我去上厕所
I need to make water.
你不可能逃得出多斯拉克人的地盘
You can't run from Dothraki
你也清楚这一点
You know this.
我从没想过逃离多斯拉克人
I will never run from Dothraki
去 给她带路
Go, show her.
我需要呼吸点新鲜空气
I needed fresh air.
老女人太臭了
The old women stink.
她们确实招人恶心
They do stink.
你的卡奥死时你一定非常年轻
You must have been very young when your Khal died.
十六岁
Sixteen.
可惜他没死得更早
Too bad he didn't die sooner.
没错 真是可惜
Yes, too bad.
你真的有三条龙吗？
Is it true you have three dragons?
他们会吐火吗？
And they breathe fire?
会
They do.
你想有朝一日亲眼看一看他们吗？
Would you like to see them one day?
我是一个多希卡林
I am Dosh Khaleen.
我无法离开维斯·多斯拉克 直到我生命结束 化为火葬台上的一缕轻烟
I can never leave Vaes Dothrak, until I rise as smoke from the pyre on the day I die.
- 住手 不要伤害她 - 她会出卖我们
- No, don't hurt her. - She'll give us away.
我们现在得走了
We have to go now.
我们不可能从维斯·多斯拉克活着出去
We will never get out of Vaes Dothrak alive.
我们所能做的就是奋力一搏
All we can do is try.
不
No.
我们所能做的比那多得多
We can do more than that.
而你们要助我一臂之力
And you're going to help me.
至于你……
And you...
请对我有信心 卡丽熙
Have faith in me, Khaleesi.
不要背叛我
Do not betray me.
玛格丽·提利尔
王后
如果我现在让你离开 你会去哪里？
If I were to let you leave right now, where would you go?
你会去找寻什么？
What would you seek out?
我会去见我的哥哥
I'd go to my brother,
我的丈夫 我的家人
my husband, my family.
那是自然 但对你而言 这就意味着找寻金钱
Of course, but for you, that means seeking out money,
大麻雀
总主教
华服 权柄
finery, power.
找寻家人即是找寻罪恶
Seeking out your family means seeking out sin.
我并不是诋毁你
I'm not maligning you.
我也曾追寻那些东西
I sought those things out, too.
重视他们超过一切
To the exclusion of all else.
我父亲是鞋匠
My father was a cobbler.
他在我年轻时去世  我继承了他的店
He died when I was young and I took over his shop.
他是个简单的人  做的鞋也很简便
He was a simple man and he made simple shoes.
可是我后来发现  我在制鞋上的功夫用的越多
But I found that the more work I put into my shoes,
卖的也就越好
the more people wanted them.
上好的皮革 装饰
Fine leather, ornamentation,
细节设计以及花费的时间
detailing, and time.
尤其是时间
Time most of all.
花去几十个钟头来制作一双鞋
Dozens of hours spent on a single pair.
品质需要时间
Quality takes time.
确实如此
Yes.
我估计你一直都穿着某人花去一整年时间
I imagine you've worn a year
所制成的鞋
of someone's life on your back.
贵族喜欢用我的生命去呵护他们的脚
The highborn liked to cover their feet with my time
而且他们对此也给予丰厚的报酬
and they paid well for the privilege.
我用他们给的钱
I used their money
去为自己购买机会 享受他们那种生活
to buy a taste of their lives for myself.
每当我沉溺于此
Each time I indulged,
我都能感觉自己变得更好了
I felt myself ascending to something better.
后有某日汝穿过墓园
And one day you walked through a graveyard
顿悟世事皆为浮云
and realized it was all for nothing
乃下决心追逐正义
and set out on the path to righteousness.
陌客之书，第25节
Book of the Stranger, verse 25.
你知道《七星圣经》？
You know "The Seven-Pointed Star."
乌尼亚修女给我读过   她无时不刻不在读
Septa Unella reads it to me. At me.
是的  是的  她确实喜欢对人宣讲
Yes, yes, she does enjoy reading at people.
你说的差不多
You're close.
不过那不是墓园
But it wasn't a graveyard.
而是一场盛宴
It was a feast.
我买了好酒陈酿
I bought old fine wine
还有很多年轻漂亮的女孩
and young pretty girls
邀请朋友们前来 一起分享
and invited my friends to come and share it all.
我们分享美酒  分享女人
We passed around the wine, passed around the women,
陷入了恍惚状态
and soon we fell into a stupor.
我在黎明前醒来
I woke before dawn.
几乎不能站直身
I could barely stand.
其他所有人都在长椅或者地上睡着
Everyone else was asleep on the couches or on the floor,
乱七八糟地睡在他们昂贵的衣服旁边
lying in heaps next to their fine clothes.
他们的身体一览无余
The truth of their bodies laid bare.
我可以闻到他们
I could smell them
透过熏香和香水
beneath the incense and the perfume
还有美味佳肴已经开始变质的味道
and the fine food that had already started to turn.
我非常清晰地看到了这一切
And I saw it with perfect clarity.
我看到了我的罪
I saw what my sins were.
我拥有的金子  我喝过的酒  我上过的女人
The gold I had, the wine I drank, the women I used,
我为保住地位而做出的不懈努力
my ceaseless struggle to maintain my position.
这都成了故事的一部分
It was all part of a story.
一个我用来告诫自己“我是谁？”的故事
A story I was telling myself about who I was.
一个在光明之下无所遁形的
A collection of lies
谎言的集合
that would disappear in the light.
那些我曾避之唯恐不及的人
The people I was trying to climb away from,
街上的乞丐
the beggars in the street,
穷苦人
the poor,
他们比曾经的我更加接近真实
they were closer to the truth than I ever was.
所以你做了什么？
So what did you do?
我离开过去的生活 前去找寻他们
I left to go and find them.
我甚至连鞋都没穿
I didn't even put on my shoes.
我走出了门就再也没回去
I walked out the door and never went back.
来吧  我们去看看他
Come, let's go and see him.
-谁？  -你哥哥
- Who? - Your brother.
洛拉斯
Loras.
听我说
Listen to me.
你必须保持坚强
You need to stay strong.
洛拉斯·提利尔
百花骑士
我根本坚强不了
I can't stay strong.
我从没坚强过
I never was strong.
你很坚强
You are strong.
你是我们家族的未来
You are the future of our house,
我们血脉的未来
the future of our family.
我才不在乎那个
I don't care about that.
你难道...你难道告诉他们那个了？
Have you... have you told them that?
告诉他们你不在乎？
That you don't care?
我只想一切停下来
I just want it to stop.
帮帮我
Help me.
他们想让我帮你
They want me to help you.
他们想让我帮忙  把你逼疯
They want me to help tear you down.
这就是为什么他让我来看你  我知道会是这样
That's why he's letting me see you. I know it is.
如果我们之中谁屈从于他们  他们就赢了
And if either of us give in to what they want, then they win.
让他们赢吧
Let them win.
只要让一切停止就行
Just make it stop.
求你了
Please.
好吧
All right.
在当前的窘境下 如何避免灾难的降临
And now, how to avert disaster with our current predicament.
这个大麻雀
This High Sparrow.
瑟曦·兰尼斯特
太后
陛下  我应付过各种各样的狂信徒
I have dealt with fanatics of every description, Your Grace.
不要激怒他们  这是最重要的事情
Not setting them off, that's the most important thing.
你已经深陷内部和外部的敌人包围了
You are beset with enemies both within and without.
你在这里做什么？
What are you doing here?
我就当前的窘境来给国王提供谏言
I am advising the king on our current predicament.
-出去  -我可是御前重臣
- Leave. - I am a member of the small council.
托曼·拜拉席恩一世
国王
派席尔
大学士
陛下
The king...
这是御前会议吗？
Is this a small council meeting?
显然不是
Obviously not.
我来这是奉献我的智慧和支持
I'm here to lend my wisdom and my support.
感谢你的谏言  国师
Thank you for your counsel, Grand Maester.
今天就到此为止吧
That will be all for now.
陛下
Your Grace.
鉴于我错过了之前多次御前会议
Since I've missed the past several small council meetings,
我想与你讨论几件事
I wanted to speak to you about a few things.
我一直在思考大麻雀
I've been thinking about the High Sparrow.
彼此彼此 真不幸
As have we all, unfortunately.
我们和这样一个人打交道时必须小心
We need to be careful in dealing with such a man.
避免事态进一步升级
To prevent things from escalating any further.
避免与其敌对
We have to be careful not to antagonize him.
他手上押着玛格丽  我们不能拿她冒险
He has Margaery. We can't put her at risk.
-他很危险  -看着我
- He's dangerous. - Look at me.
他们对我做了什么？
What did they do to me?
对国王的亲生母亲？
To the king's own mother?
算了
It's all right.
已经过去了  成了过去时
It's done. It's in the past.
而且确实
And of course
玛格丽的安全是第一位的
Margaery's safety is paramount.
你不喜欢玛格丽  对吧？
You don't like Margaery, do you?
我喜不喜欢她根本无关紧要
Whether I like her or not is completely unimportant.
玛格丽是王后
Margaery is the queen.
王后要有尊严  国王更须如此
Queens must command respect. Kings even more so.
这不仅仅是为了他们  更是为了所有人
Not just for their own sake, but for everyone's.
大麻雀对国王和王后没有尊重
The High Sparrow has no respect for kings or queens.
对世上任何事情都没有尊重
No respect for anything in this world.
他根本不在乎世上的一切存在
He has no use for the things of this world.
他想将一切扳倒  然后用什么来取而代之？
He wants to knock them down and replace them with what?
用幻想
With fantasies.
用街上的乞丐
With beggars in the street.
用虚妄
With nothing.
母亲……
Mother...
有些事我想告诉您
there's something I want to tell you.
大麻雀告诉我的事
Something the High Sparrow told me.
你和他谈过了？
You've spoken with him?
我答应过他不会告诉任何人  如果他发现我……
I promised him I wouldn't tell anyone. If he found out I told...
那就是他不会轻易饶恕的泄密行为了
It would be a breach of confidence which he would not take lightly
瞧瞧他天天宣讲做人的真实
given his constant prattling about the truth.
我是你的母亲
I am your mother.
你永远可以信任我
You can always trust me.
根据国王陛下的命令 御前会议推迟举行
The small council meeting has been postponed on the king's orders.
奥莲娜·雷德温
荆棘女王
凯冯·兰尼斯特
国王之手
我还以为我们第一次会面时已经说得很清楚了
I would have thought we were perfectly clear the first time.
-你在这里不受欢迎  -你说过你尊重我们的父亲
- You're not welcome. - You once spoke of your respect for our father
詹姆·兰尼斯特
御林铁卫
是因为他懂得和对手一起共事的重要性
because he understood the necessity of working with one's rivals.
亲爱的  你已经毫无尊严和权威可言
My dear, you have been stripped of your dignity and authority,
公开羞辱 然后软禁在红堡
publically shamed, and confined to the Red Keep.
还有什么共事的资本？
What's left to work with?
瑟曦是国王的母亲
Cersei is the mother of the king.
国王肯听她的意见 也信任她
She has the king's ear and his trust.
并且国王最近经常和大麻雀一起讨论
And the king has been speaking regularly
玛格丽王后和洛拉斯爵士
with the High Sparrow about Queen Margaery and Ser Loras.
大麻雀能够攫取权力
The High Sparrow seized power
正因为看透了我们只会在内部争吵而不是将其夺回
knowing full well we'd bicker amongst ourselves instead of seizing it back.
下场如此  我们真不赖
Here we are. Well done to us.
现在七国的未来
Now the future of the Seven Kingdoms
全操于他肮脏的农民之手
rests in his dirty peasant hands.
几天后  他将对我进行审判
In a few days, he'll have a trial for me.
不过在此之前  玛格丽王后要先进行赎罪之旅
But before that, Queen Margaery will make her walk of atonement.
是的  玛格丽将要当着全城的善男信女的面
Yes, Margaery will repent her sins
忏悔罪行
before the good people of the city.
哦  不
Oh, no.
这事不能发生
That cannot happen.
不会发生
That will not happen.
我同意
I agree.
你有维斯特洛大陆第二多的军队
You've got the second largest army in Westeros.
你将带他们进城
You'll bring them into the city,
在玛格丽王后被羞辱之前阻止它发生
stop Queen Margaery's humiliation before it starts,
并将她带回王宫监护
and take her back into Crown custody.
为了王后的安全 国王已命我不要采取任何针对大麻雀
The king has ordered me to take no action against the High Sparrow
或教团武装的行动
or the Faith Militant out of fear for the queen's safety.
你无需行动
You will take no action at all.
当提利尔军队来的时候  你让开就是
When the Tyrell armies come, you will stand down.
国王的命令严格要求您不能让开吗？
Are you expressly forbidden from standing down?
是的  不过如果国王……
No, but if the king should call...
整个事件将在任何人要求你做任何事情之前结束
The whole thing will be over before anyone can call on you to do anything.
那时大麻雀已被监禁 最好是死了
When the High Sparrow is in custody or dead, preferably,
玛格丽已回到托曼身边
and Margaery's back at Tommen's side,
你觉得国王会对结果生气吗？
do you think the king will be angry at the outcome?
你和我们一样讨厌这些狂信徒
You hate these fanatics as much as we do.
你恨他们对你儿子的所作所为
You hate what they've done to your son.
你想要蓝塞尔回来吗？
Do you want Lancel back?
还是说你已经彻底放弃他了？
Or have you given him up for good?
我当然想要他回来
Of course I want him back.
那就让开吧
Then stand aside
让那些将他从你身边夺走的人付出代价
and let the people that took him from you be destroyed.
如果一切没有按计划进行
If it doesn't go as planned,
麻雀们在城里有很多盟友
the sparrows have many friends in this city.
内战将会爆发   很多人会死
We'll have civil war. Many will die.
无论我们做什么都会有很多人死去
Many will die no matter what we do.
他们死好过咱们死
Better them than us.
席恩·葛雷乔伊
他们说你回来了 我不信
They told me you were home and I didn't believe it.
我说 “席恩·葛雷乔伊吗？”
"Theon Greyjoy?" I said.
“他死了”
"He's dead.
“他死了很久了”
He's been dead a long time."
他放你走的？
He let you go?
亚拉·葛雷乔伊
我逃出来的
I escaped.
我听不清
I can't hear you.
我逃出来的
I escaped.
看着我
Look at me.
看着我！
Look at me!
好多人为了救你而死
Men died trying to rescue you.
他们都是好人
Good men.
我的人
My men.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你曾是我的弟弟
You were my brother.
你是个被宠坏了的混蛋 但你是我弟弟
You were a spoiled little cunt, but you were my brother
我为你赌上了一切
and I risked everything for you
你却背叛了我
and you betrayed me.
我知道 我知道 我对不起你
I know. I know and I'm sorry.
别说了
Stop saying that.
他让我崩溃了
He broke me.
他让我崩溃成了无数碎片
He broke me into 1,000 pieces.
- 我知道 -你不知道
- I know. - You don't know.
他送了一片给我们
He sent us one of those pieces.
所以我才去救你
That's why I came for you.
你为什么回来
Why did you come here?
我还有什么地方可去？
Where else could I go?
你听到父亲死了 就想回来争夺王位吗？
You heard Father was dead and you thought you'd claim the crown?
不 不是的  入港之后我才知道他去世了
No, no. I only heard he died after we docked.
恰好在选王会之前回到派克岛？
You happen to show up on Pyke right before the kingsmoot?
我不知道这事
I didn't know.
你觉得你搞了那些事情出来后
You think any ironborn wants you to be king
还会有铁民想要拥戴你？
after what you've done?
我不想当国王
I don't want to be king.
你想要什么？
What do you want?
我应该听你的话 你是唯一一个……
I should have listened to you. You're the only one...
无所谓了 别哭了
That doesn't matter anymore. Stop crying.
看着我
Look at me.
告诉我你到底想要什么
Tell me what you want.
你应该统治铁群岛
You should rule the Iron Islands.
让我来帮你
Let me help you.
他们把你收拾得挺干净
They've cleaned you up nicely.
你知道我是谁吗
You know who I am?
一个老爷
A lord.
是的
Yes.
拉姆斯·波顿
一个老爷
A lord.
你见过我的家徽吗？
You've seen my banners?
欧莎
野人
剥皮人
The flayed man.
你害怕吗？
Does that worry you at all?
剥皮后你会吃人吗？
You eat them after?
不会
No.
我可是见过人吃人
Then I've seen worse.
你服侍过史塔克家？
You served the Starks?
是的 他们用链子锁着我
Aye. They put me in chains
拿剑抵在我的喉咙上
and put a sword at my throat,
所以我服侍他们
so I served them.
史塔克家族覆灭已久
The Starks have been gone for a long time,
但你一直保护着瑞肯
but you kept protecting Rickon.
找得到合适的买家 他能卖个好价钱
He'd fetch a good price to the right buyer.
我服侍他家族那么久
I served his family a long time.
一点钱都没捞到
Didn't get no wages.
依我看 这是他们欠我的
Way I see it, I'm owed.
话虽如此
Be that as it may,
瑞肯再也不是你可以卖的了
Rickon's not yours to sell anymore.
他是我的了
He's mine.
所以你现在还有什么用呢？
So what use could I possibly have for you?
我可以给你你想要的
I can give you what you want.
你真的知道我想要什么吗？
And you're sure you know what that is?
男人都想要一个东西
Same thing men always want.
男人想要的时候 就会先给她洗个澡
And when they really want it, they give it a bath first.
你真会说话
You're a good talker.
我喜欢
I like that.
你比席恩·葛雷乔伊会说多了
You're a much better talker than Theon Greyjoy.
是吗？
That so?
让他开口说话真费劲
I had to work hard to get him talking.
但他还是说了
But he talked.
他们都会说的
They all do.
他什么都说了
He told me everything.
史塔克家男孩们的一切
All about the Stark boys,
谁帮他们逃跑
who helped them escape,
她是怎么帮的
and how she did it.
开门！
Open the gate!
吃的不好 抱歉
Sorry about the food.
我们可不以美食闻名
It's not what we're known for.
没关系 你们有更重要的事
That's all right. There are more important things.
你的信 总司令大人
A letter for you, Lord Commander.
我已经不是总司令了
I'm not Lord Commander anymore.
叛徒及野种琼恩·雪诺
"To the traitor and bastard Jon Snow.
你让数以千计的野人越过了绝境长城
You allowed thousands of wildlings past the Wall.
你背叛了自己人
You have betrayed your own kind.
你背叛了北境
You have betrayed the North.
临冬城是我的 野种 来看看吧
Winterfell is mine, bastard. Come and see.
你弟弟瑞肯在我的地牢里
Your brother Rickon is in my dungeon.
他的冰原狼的皮铺在我的地板上
His direwolf's skin is on my floor.
来看看吧 我要我的新娘
Come and see. I want my bride back.
交出她 野种 我便不找你或你的野人朋友们的麻烦
Send her to me, bastard, and I will not trouble you or your wildling lovers.
如若不肯 我会向北进军 大肆屠戮
Keep her from me and I will ride north and slaughter
所有在你庇护之下的野人 不管是男人 女人或小孩
every wildling man, woman, and babe living under your protection.
我会当着你的面活剥他们 我会……
You will watch as I skin them living. You... "
继续
Go on.
都是类似的话
It's just more of the same.
让你眼睁睁地看着我的士兵轮奸你的妹妹
"You will watch as my soldiers take turns raping your sister.
我会让你眼睁睁的看着我的狗
You will watch as my dogs
吃了你狂野的幼弟
devour your wild little brother.
然后我会挖出你的眼睛 剩下的留给我的狗
Then I will spoon your eyes from their sockets and let my dogs do the rest.
来看看吧 拉姆斯·波顿 临冬城公爵和
Come and see. Ramsay Bolton, Lord of Winterfell
北境守护
and Warden of the North."
临冬城公爵和北境守护
Lord of Winterfell and Warden of the North.
他父亲死了
His father's dead.
拉姆斯杀了他
Ramsay killed him.
- 现在他手里还有瑞肯 - 我们不能确定
- And now he has Rickon. - We don't know that.
不 可以确定
Yes, we do.
他有多少兵？
How many men does he have in his army?
他说起史坦尼斯的进攻时 提到有五千人
I heard him say 5,000 once when he was talking about Stannis's attack.
你有多少人？
How many do you have?
能行军打仗的？
That can march and fight?
二千
2,000.
剩下的是小孩和老人
The rest are children and old people.
你是真正的北境守护之子
You're the son of the last true Warden of the North.
北境家族都很忠诚 只要你要求 他们会和你并肩战斗
Northern families are loyal. They'll fight for you if you ask.
那个魔鬼抢走了我们的家 我们的弟弟
A monster has taken our home and our brother.
我们必须回到临冬城 把他们都抢回来
We have to go back to Winterfell and save them both.
圣城中禁止流血
It is forbidden to spill blood in the sacred city.
也禁止携带武器
It is forbidden to <i>carry weapons</i> in the sacred city.
所以我们不流血
So we don't spill blood!
嗯……也总不能一点血都不流吗
Well... there's always a little blood.
萨沃卡奥
有人用石头砸烂了他的头
Someone crushed his head with a rock.
阿戈属于我的卡拉萨
Aggo belonged to my khalasar.
他很干的很好
He served me well.
他被人用石头砸烂了头
He got his head smashed in by a rock.
去他的阿戈
Fuck Aggo.
把卓戈的遗孀带上来
Bring in Drogo's widow.
谁看得上她？她是个矮子
Who cares about her? She's a midget.
我喜欢她
I like her.
她比牛奶还惨白
She's paler than milk.
我想尝尝卡丽熙是什么滋味
I'd like to know what a khaleesi tastes like.
好啊
Good.
尝尝我的小兄弟就知道了
You can suck my dick.
她属于多希卡林
She belongs with the Dosh Khaleen.
渊凯的贤主大人们想要她
The Wise Masters of Yunkai want her.
他们想用一万匹马交换
They're offering ten thousand horses in exchange.
哪个更值钱
What's worth more,
一个粉嘟嘟的小女孩儿 还是一万匹马
one pink little girl or ten thousand horses?
操他贤主大人的香屁股
Fuck the Wise Masters in their perfumed asses.
要马我自己会抢
I'll take their horses for myself.
你们不想听听我的想法吗？
Don't you want to know what I think?
你想被卖了当奴隶？
You'd rather be sold into slavery?
还是想给拉寇尝尝你的滋味
Or maybe you'd like to show Rhalko here what you taste like?
不想
No.
哪个都不想
I don't want either of those things.
你想不想我们不在乎
We don't care what you want.
这是多希卡林神庙
This is the Temple of the Dosh Khaleen.
这没你说话的份儿
You have no voice here,
除非你是多希卡林
unless you are Dosh Khaleen.
但你不是 除非我们认定你是
Which you are not, until we decide you are.
我知道我在哪 我来过这儿
I know where I am. I have been here before.
多希卡林在这儿预言我的孩子会成为骑着世界的骏马
This is where the Dosh Khaleen pronounced my child the Stallion Who Mounts the World.
然后呢？
And what happened?
你像傻瓜一样 竟然相信一个巫魔女
You trusted a sorceress, like a fool.
因为你 你的孩子死了
Your baby is dead because of you.
卓戈卡奥也死了
And so is Khal Drogo.
在这儿卓戈发誓要带着他的卡拉萨向西走到世界尽头
This is where Drogo promised to take his khalasar west to where the world ends.
骑着木马横渡黑色咸水 做出古往今来其他卡奥都从来没有做过的事
To ride wooden horses across the Black Salt Sea as no khal has done before.
他发誓要杀死穿铁衣服的人 拆了他们的石头房子
He promised to kill the men in their iron suits and tear down their stone houses.
他在圣母山前对我发誓
He swore to me before the Mother of Mountains.
你竟然蠢到相信他
And you were dumb enough to believe him.
此时此地 伟大的卡奥们在讨论什么？
And here, now, what great matters do the Great Khals discuss?
抢劫哪个小村子
Which little villages you'll raid,
能骑多少个姑娘 该要求多少匹骏马作贡品
how many girls you'll get to fuck, how many horses you'll demand in tribute.
你们都是小人物
You are small men.
你们不配领导多斯拉克人
None of you are fit to lead the Dothraki.
但我配
But I am.
而我也将领导
So I will.
好
All right.
你不用当多希卡林了
No Dosh Khaleen for you.
我们轮流上你
Instead we'll take turns fucking you.
然后让我们的血盟卫上你
And then we'll let our bloodriders fuck you.
你要是还撑得住
And if there's anything left of you,
再给我们的马一个机会
we'll give our horses a turn.
疯婊子
You crazy cunt.
你真以为我们会臣服于你？
Did you really think we would serve you?
你们不用臣服
You're not going to serve.
你们会死
You're not going to die.
衣柜字幕组出品
剧情没看懂？ 典故不清楚？
维基新站网址：HTTP://AsoIaF.HuiJi.WiKi
本集关键字：陌客之书